Register of the Price family papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Price family papers
1793-2004
(bulk 1856-2004)
82061
Price family.
17 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The Price family papers are comprised of correspondence, writings, diaries, orders, memoranda, genealogical material, printed matter, notes, photographs, and memorabilia, documenting several generations of the Price family. Due to the diverse careers of the family and their residence in different countries, the collection provides an international account of events spanning from Victorian England to the late 20th century United States. Material relates to missionary work in Madagascar, 1875-1882; German prisoners of war in Siberia during World War I; the Russian Revolution; social conditions in China; Allied secret service and radio propaganda activities in World War II; and London during the Blitz.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Malagasy subject collection, 1902-1998. Hoover Institution Archives
Carl Bartram photograph collection, 1944-1995. Hoover Institution Archives
Marvin R. Edwards papers, 1942-2004. Hoover Institution Archives
Imprisonment in Siberia, ca. 1920. Hoover Institution Archives
Kreisverband Jena records, 1917-1976. Hoover Institution Archives
Shtab photographs, 1916. Hoover Institution Archives
Joyce N. Laxalt album, 1914-1917. Hoover Institution Archives
Hereward Thimbleby Price papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Biographical/Historical Note
Charles Thomas Price (1847-1933) was educated at Cheshunt College, Cambridge. He was ordained as a Congregational minister on January 25, 1875, and married Mary Anne (Polly) Thimbleby on February 28. The couple sailed for Madagascar on March 25, 1875, where Charles Price served as a missionary for six years, and where his sons Egbert and Hereward were born. He was widowed and remarried in 1901 to Annie Beatrice Hill. After returning to England in 1882, he ministered to several congregations including: Lenham in Kent (1883-1890), Buckingham (1890-1901), Ross-on-Wye (1901-1910), and East Grinstead (1910-1914). His last congregation was at Reigate in Surrey (1916-1925), where he died in 1933.
Hereward Thimbleby Price was born in Madagascar in 1880. He studied at Oxford, where he received his B.A. and M.A. and worked on the Oxford English Dictionary. He moved to Germany in 1904, where he taught English at the Universities of Kiel and Bonn, and studied under Bülbring for his Ph.D. While in Bonn he met Elisabeth (Liese) Prym (1884-1971), who became his wife in 1911. Their son Arnold was born in 1912. Drafted into the German army in 1915, Hereward Price was captured on the eastern front by Russia and sent to a prisoner of war camp in Siberia. After his escape, he traveled across Russia to China, where he worked briefly at the Anglo-Chinese College of Tientsin before returning to his family in England via Japan and Canada. Hereward moved to the United States and became a professor of English at the University of Michigan in 1929. He became a distinguished scholar of Shakespeare, and died in 1964.
Egbert Thimbleby Price (Bret) was the son of Charles, brother of Hereward. He was born in June of 1876. He was educated at the Eltham School and Silcontes School in Wakefield. He began working at the Hearts of Oak Benefit Society in 1892, transferred to Barclay's Bank in 1895, and worked for a succession of banks and businesses until 1923. During this period he traveled widely, spending time in Berlin and South America. From 1923-1925 he lived in London, then returned to the business world until 1936 by buying a partnership in Sedgwick and Co. of Colombo. After his return to England, he worked in publications for the Institute of Sociology (1936-1938), as Editor of the Digest of Charities (1938-1940), at the Censor in the Foreign Office (1940-1946), and at the Post Office Savings Department (1946-1949). He died July 5, 1949.
Arnold Hereward Price was born in Bonn, Germany, on July 1, 1912. He came to the United States after finishing high school in Germany in 1933. Joining his parents in Ann Arbor, he became a specialist in Modern European History at the University of Michigan, receiving his A.B. in 1935, his M.A. in 1936. He married Alice Price in 1938, and from 1939 to 1941 acted as assistant supervisor of the University's archaeological laboratory in Detroit. After the lab shut down, he worked for the department of English as a research assistant on the Early Modern English Proverb Dictionary (1941-1942), and received his Ph.D. in 1942. Arnold Price then moved to Washington D.C., where he worked for the Library of Congress, specializing in Central Europe. In 1943, he left the Library of Congress and began his service with the Army, in the Office of Strategic Services, which lasted until 1946. At the conclusion of World War II, Arnold Price transferred to the Department of State until 1960. He returned to the Library of Congress from 1960 to 1979 as an area specialist for Central Europe, then performed bibliographic work for the American Historical Association until 1991. In addition to his professional duties, Arnold Price also lectured at the University of New Mexico (1947-1948) and American University (1948, 1959), and was section editor of the American Historical Review from 1961 through the 1980s. He was divorced from Alice in 1970, remarried Elizabeth Beitz, was widowed in 1986, and remarried again in 1991 to Dana Dinkins.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Price family papers are comprised of correspondence, writings, diaries, orders, memoranda, genealogical material, printed matter, notes, photographs, and memorabilia, documenting several generations of the Price family. Due to the diverse careers of the family and their residence in different countries, the collection provides an international account of events spanning from Victorian England to the late 20th century United States. Material relates to missionary work in Madagascar, 1875-1882; German prisoners of war in Siberia during World War I; the Russian Revolution; social conditions in China; Allied secret service and radio propaganda activities in World War II; and London during the Blitz.
The collection is arranged into series by family member. The first series documents the life of Charles T. Price: his studies, missionary work, return to England, and retirement. It also contains a small amount of correspondence dated during World War I concerning his son Hereward. The second series depicts Hereward Price's service in the German army during World War I, his sojourn in a Russian POW camp, and his subsequent travels through Siberia and China on his way home. The Egbert Price series contains correspondence with his brother Hereward and his sister Dorothea (children of Charles T. Price), describing conditions in London during World War II. The fourth series encompasses Arnold Price's work during World War II with the Office of Strategic Services, the State Department, his research interests, and his efforts to compile genealogical information about the Price and Prym families. The photographs series contains material relating to all of the family members, including photographs of the Price family, their friends, travels, and the mission in Madagascar.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: Charles T. Price papers, 1856-1989; Hereward T. Price papers, 1900-1999; Egbert T. Price papers, 1917-1950; Arnold H. Price papers, 1793-2004; and Photographs, 1860-2001.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
United States. Office of Strategic Services.; United States. Dept. of State.; Germany. Heer.; Missions--Madagascar.; Prisoners of war.; World War, 1914-1918--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.; Secret service--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; Propaganda, American.; China--Social conditions.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; United States--Foreign relations.; Missionaries.; Price, Charles T. (Charles Thomas); Price, Hereward Thimbleby, 1880-1964.; Price, Arnold Hereward, 1912-
Collection Contents
- Charles T. Price papers, 1831-1989. [bulk 1856-1933] (Box 1-2, 8)
  Includes diary of Charles Price's missionary work in Madagascar, correspondence, notes from his college days in Cheshunt College at Cambridge, published material, Sunday school medals, a Malagasy spindle and charm to ward against the evil eye. The Charles Price series primarily documents his studies, missionary work, and retirement; it also contains a small amount of correspondence dated during World War I concerning his son Hereward. Arranged by document type.
  - Cheshunt College notebook, 1874 June 9 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1856-1865 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Correspondence - Cheshunt College, 1870-1874 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Correspondence - Madagascar, 1875-1881 (Folder 1: 4-5)
  - Correspondence, 1903-1921 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Correspondence - Reigate, 1922-1933 (Folder 1: 7-11)
  - Correspondence regarding leaving Madagascar, 1932 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Correspondence to Hereward, 1915-1933 (Folder 1: 13-16)
  - Correspondence and notes on publication of diary, 1988 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Diary of Mr. C.T.P., 1875-1877 (Folder 2: 2-3)
  - Jubilee at Buckingham, 1907 (Folder 2: 4)
  - List of places preached, 1881-1883 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Notes on typescript of diary, 1933 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Prelude in A by Rinck, undated (Folder 2: 7)
  - Published material, 1871-1989 (Folder 2)
    - Antananarivo Annual, 1875; 1886 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Missionary to the Malagasy: The Madagascar Diary of the Rev. Charles T. Price, 1875-1877, edited by Arnold H. Price. New York: Peter Lang Inc., 1989 (Folder 2: 9)
    - North-East Madagascar: A Narrative of a Missionary Tour, by Reverend J. A. Houlder. Antananarivo: London Missionary Society Press, 1877 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Ny Fiherana, 1882 (Folder 8)
    - Ny Soratra Masina. London: British and Foreign Bible Society, 1871 (Folder 2: 11)
      Translation of the Bible into Malagasy
    - South-East Madagascar: Being Notes of a Journey through the Tanala, Taimoro, and Taisaka Countries, in June and July, 1876, by James Sibree, Jr. Antananarivo: Abraham Kingdon (Folder 2: 12)
    - Ten Years' Review of Mission Work in Madagascar, 1880-1890. Antananarivo: London Missionary Society (Folder 2: 13)
    - Teny Soa. Antananarivo: London Missionary Society, 1882 (Folder 3: 1)
      In Malagasy.
    - Tiona Ela Sy Vao, by Reverend J. Richardson and Reverend C. T. Price. Antananarivo: London Missionary Society, 1879 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Vatsim-Panahin' Ny Mpiantafika. Paris: Société des Missions Evangéliques de Paris, 1917 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Memorabilia, 1831-1880 (Box 8)
    - Sunday School medals, 1831-1866 (Box 8)
    - Cartes-de-visite photographs of Cheshunt College friends, circa 1874 (Box 8)
    - Malagasy spindle, circa 1880 (Box 8)
    - Charm to ward off the evil eye, circa 1880 (Box 8)
    - Wax seal, undated (Box 8)
- Hereward T. Price papers, 1900-1999. (Box 3-9)
  Contains correspondence, postcard books depicting his travels, clippings, articles, and published material. Records Hereward Price's service in the German army during World War I, his sojourn in a Russian POW camp, and his subsequent travels through Siberia and China on his way home. Includes a substantial amount of correspondence with his wife (Liese Price) and other family members, showing their efforts to locate and assist him after his capture. Arranged by document type. The correspondence is further arranged by name.
  - Correspondence, 1900-1949. (Folder 3)
    Arranged by correspondent's last name
    - Entschedé, Matilda, 1915-1919 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Entschedé, Matilda to Charles T. Price, 1915-1916 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Farquharson, Dorothea Price to Hereward Price, 1916-1933 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Farquharson, Dorothea Price, 1914-1917. (Folder 3: 7-11, Folder 4: 1-10, Folder 5: 1-4)
      Includes correspondence among Dorothea (Dodo), Charles, Liese, and Hereward Price. Concerns aiding Hereward while he is abroad and repatriating him. Collected and annotated by Dorothea.
    - Farquharson, Dorothea Price, extracts from Hereward's letters, 1917-1918 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Price, Hereward to Arnold, 1916-1919 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Price, Hereward to Charles, 1900-1933 (Folder 5: 7-9)
    - Price, Hereward to Liese, 1915-1916 (Folder 5: 10-11)
    - Price, Hereward to Liese, 1917 (Folder 6: 1)
    - Price, Hereward, postcards, 1917 (Folder 6: 2)
    - Price, Hereward, 1918 (Folder 6: 3)
    - Price, Liese, 1915-1919 (Folder 6: 4-8)
    - New English Dictionary correspondence, 1918-1949 (Folder 6: 9)
    - Other correspondents, 1914-1932 (Folder 6: 10-12)
    - Testimonial correspondence, 1903-1917 (Folder 7: 1)
    - Clippings, 1919-1951 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Diary of the War, 1914-1919 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Hereward Price and Liese Price, as told to their grandchildren on the occasion of their Golden Wedding, 1961, 1999 (Folder 7: 4)
    - Oxford documents, 1900-1909 (Folder 7: 5)
    - Postcards, undated (Folder 7: 6)
    - Ration cards, 1919 (Folder 7: 7)
      In German
    - Travel documents, 1904-1919 (Folder 7: 8)
    - Travel reports, 1929-1930 (Folder 7: 9)
    - University of Bonn - Certificates of study, 1905-1907. (Folder 7: 10)
  - Miscellany, 1906-1918 (Folder 7: 11)
    - War memorabilia, undated. (Box 8)
      Includes bone medal and Afrikakorps armband
  - Published material, 1919-1950. (Folder 7)
    In chronological order
    - Bibliography, undated (Folder 7: 12)
    - Tipy Zabaikal'ia, and Vidy Krugobaikal'ia, postcard sets, undated. (Folder 7: 13)
      In Russian
    - Stozh M. E. Irkutsk do pervago gubernatora, essay, 1916 (Folder 7: 14)
    - Tovarishch, calendar/planner for 1917/1918 (Folder 7: 15)
    - The Cornhill Magazine, 1919 November (Folder 7: 16)
    - The Median, 1921 (Folder 7: 17)
    - Erinnerungsblätter deutscher Regimenter, 2 Kurhessisches Infanterie - Regiment Nr. 82, 1922 (Folder 7: 18)
    - The Dream by H.G. Wells and The Innocence of Father Brown by G.K. Chesterton, 1926 (Folder 7: 19)
    - Economic Dictionary by Dr. Hereward T. Price, 1926 (Folder 9: 1)
      In English and German
    - Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review, 1940, 1945 (Folder 9: 2)
    - Emory University Quarterly, 1950 June (Folder 9: 3)
- Egbert T. Price papers, 1917-1950. (Box 9)
  Includes correspondence written by Egbert (Bret) Price, primarily to his brother Hereward and his sister Dorothea Price Farquharson. Describes conditions in London during World War II. Arranged by correspondent.
  - Correspondence to Dorothea, 1917-1950 (Folder 9: 4-10)
  - Correspondence to Hereward, 1920-1949 (Folder 9: 11)
- Arnold H. Price papers, 1793-2004. (Box 8-18)
  Consists of correspondence, notes, reports, clippings, and printed material illustrating Arnold Price's work during World War II with the Office of Strategic Services, the State Department, his research interests, and his efforts to compile genealogical information about the Price and Prym families. Arranged in five subseries: Genealogical material, 1793-1999; Government work files, 1942-1979; Published material and writings, 1935-2002; Correspondence, 1919-2003; and Subject files, 1934-2004.
  - Genealogical material, 1793-1999. (Folder 9)
    In alphabetical order
    - Alexander Alexeiev-Gigh, 1992-1999 (Folder 10: 1-2)
    - Clippings, 1903-1968 (Folder 10: 3-4)
    - Collected materials and notes, 1793, 1880-2002. (Folder 10: 5-6)
      Includes 5 livres, 10 sous, and 15 sols notes dating from the French Revolution
    - Correspondence, 1887-1985 (Folder 10: 7)
    - Free Hollow to Forest Home by Liese Price Bronfenbrenner, 1974 (Folder 10: 8)
    - Gemixte Korni: a family history for the descendents of Urie Bronfenbrenner and Liese Price, 1978 (Folder 10: 9)
    - Publication of Missionary to the Malagasy, 1962-1991 (Folder 10: 10)
    - Prym Family, 1923-1984 (Folder 10: 11-12)
    - Prym Family, 1981-1986 (Folder 11: 1)
    - University of Michigan correspondence, 1992 (Folder 11: 2)
  - Government work files, 1942-1979. (Folder 11)
    - Army/Office of Strategic Services, 1942-1947 (Folder 11: 3-4)
    - Army - transcripts of short wave broadcasts, 1943 (Folder 11: 5)
    - Fort Getty - Eine Einfuehrung in das Amerikanische Schulwesen, undated. (Folder 11: 6)
    - Fort Getty - America from the Inside, undated. (Folder 11: 7)
      In German and English
    - Fort Getty - Kleiner Führer durch Amerika, undated. (Folder 11: 8)
    - Fort Getty - "German History in a New Light" lectures, undated. (Folder 11: 9)
    - Fort Getty, 1945-1947 (Folder 11: 10)
    - Lecture Notes - German history, 1945 (Folder 11: 11-13)
    - Lecture Notes - democracy and America, 1945 (Folder 12: 1)
    - Collier's magazine article regarding teaching German prisoners of war, 1946 (Box 8)
    - State Department Office of Research and Analysis, 1948-1960 (Folder 12: 2-4)
    - Department of State Bulletin, 1949 October 17 (Folder 12: 5)
    - The Present Status of the Saar. Documents and State Papers, 1948 October (Folder 12: 6)
    - Die gegenwärtige Lage des Saarlandes, 1949 (Folder 12: 7)
    - Report on the occupation boundaries of Berlin, 1951 (Folder 12: 8)
    - Cornerstone laying of Department of State building, 1957 January 5 (Folder 12: 9)
    - State Department travel report, 1959 (Folder 12: 10)
    - Poverty rates in West Germany (study for Department of Health, Education and Welfare), 1963 (Folder 12: 11)
    - Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress, 1965 (Folder 12: 12)
    - Library of Congress publications, 1968-1979 (Folder 12: 13)
    - Library of Congress - Study of Düsseldorf rule of revolution, 1969 (Folder 12: 14)
    - Library of Congress, 1968-1984 (Folder 12: 15-17)
    - Library of Congress travel report, 1979 (Folder 12: 18)
  - Published material and writings, 1935-2002 (Folder 12)
    - The Territorial Development of the Zollverein, 1818-70, 1935 (Folder 13: 1)
    - Zollverein reviews, 1945-1951 (Folder 13: 2)
    - Miscellaneous articles, 1949-1987 (Folder 13: 3-4)
    - Reprints on German history, 1957-1982 (Folder 13: 5)
    - Monatshefte, 1959 December. (Folder 13: 6)
    - Book reviews, 1962-1992 (Folder 13: 7)
    - American Historical Association Reviews, 1965-1980 (Folder 13: 8)
    - Vierteljahrschrift für Sozial- und Wirtschaftsgeschichte, 1969-1974. (Folder 13: 9)
    - Role of the Germanic warrior clubs in the historical process, 1974 (Folder 13: 10)
    - Miscellanea Mediaevalia, 1980 (Folder 13: 11)
    - Central European History, 1981 September (Folder 13: 12)
    - Articles on libraries, 1984-2001 (Folder 13: 14)
    - The Germanic Warrior Clubs by Arnold H. Price, 1994 (Folder 13: 15)
    - The Germanic Warrior Clubs - addenda, 1998-2001 (Folder 14: 1)
    - The Germanic Warrior Clubs - notes, 1996-1998 (Folder 14: 2)
    - The Germanic Warrior Clubs - reprints, 1964-2001 (Folder 14: 3)
    - The Germanic Warrior Clubs - reviews, 1995-1997 (Folder 14: 4-5)
    - Mitteilungen der Kieler Gelehrtenschule, 1996 (Folder 14: 6)
    - Complaint against Encyclopedia Britannica, 1996-1998 (Folder 14: 7)
    - Swiss-American Historical Society Review, 1997-2000 (Folder 14: 8-9)
    - Reprints by Frank Siegmund, 2000 (Folder 14: 10)
    - American Historical Association Perspectives, 2000 September (Folder 14: 11)
    - My Twentieth Century, 2000-2002 (Folder 14: 12-13)
  - Correspondence, 1919-2003 (Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1919-2003 (Folder 15: 1-7)
    - Correspondence from Dana, 1991 (Folder 15: 8)
  - Subject files, 1934-2004. (Folder 15-18)
    Arranged in alphabetical order
    - Association for the Bibliography of History, 1979 (Folder 15: 9)
    - Bibliographies, 1964-1978 (Folder 15: 10)
    - Bibliography on Zollverein, undated., In German (Folder 15: 11)
    - Bookplate by William Beitz, undated (Folder 15: 12)
    - Boundaries of Germany during World War II, undated (Folder 15: 13)
    - Boundaries of greater Germany, 1984 (Folder 16: 1)
    - Boundaries of greater Germany - Maps, 1944 (Folder : 2)
    - Boundaries of greater Germany - News digest, undated (Folder 16: 3)
    - Boundaries of greater Germany - Notes, 1962-1979 (Folder 16: 4)
    - Boundaries of greater Germany - Publications, 1944-1974 (Folder 16: 5)
    - Boundaries of greater Germany - Stuhlpfarrer, Karl. Die Operationszonen "Alpenvorland" und "Adriatisches Küstenland." Dissertation, Universität Wien, 1967 (Folder 16: 6)
    - Clippings, 1984-1990 (Folder 16: 7)
    - Destruction of Hamburg records, 1996 (Folder 16: 8)
    - Early Germanic society, 1969-2002 (Folder 16: 9)
    - Editing Test, 1992 (Folder 16: 10)
    - German plans for Eupen, Malmedy, and Moresnet, 1940 May. (Folder 16: 11)
    - Germanic realities and projections, undated (Folder 16: 12)
    - Hildebrandlied, 1971-2002 (Folder 16: 13)
    - Historical bibliography and librarianship, 1972-1991 (Folder 17: 1)
    - Hoof Prints and Foot Prints in the Sands of Time, Describes work of the University of Michigan Archaeological Laboratory. Includes photograph, undated. (Folder 17: 2)
    - Kieler Gelehrtenschule, 1994-1997 (Folder 17: 3)
    - Chronik des Kieler Wandervogels, 1926-1929, 1996 (Folder 17: 4)
    - Kieler Wandervogel und die Hohburg zwischen 1921 und 1933, 1996. (Folder 17: 5)
    - Verein zur Erhaltung der Hohburg - Kieler Wandervogel, 1926-1997. (Folder 17: 6-7)
      In German, includes photographs
    - Memorials, 1987-2004 (Folder 17: 8)
    - Miscellaneous quotes, 1934-1991 (Folder 17: 9)
    - Miscellaneous studies on German problems, 1968, undated (Folder 17: 10)
    - Nazi Germany, 1934-1961 (Folder 17: 11)
    - Netherlands and Belgium, 1940-1971. (Folder 17: 12)
      In French
    - New Orleans police, 1984 (Folder 17: 13)
    - Die Nibelungen, 1958-1974 (Folder 17: 14)
    - Notes, 1974-2002 (Folder 17: 15)
    - OSS, 1980-1990 (Folder 17: 16)
    - OSS map, 1984 (Folder 17: 17)
    - OSS remembered, undated (Folder 17: 18)
    - Waldo in OSS: a memoir, undated (Folder 17: 19)
    - Personnel file, 1947-1986 (Folder 17: 20)
    - References submitted to publisher, undated (Folder 17: 21)
    - Report of the Tax Committee of the Prussian State Council of 1817, 1943 (Folder 17: 22)
    - Role of the Germanic warrior club in the historical process, 1974 (Folder 18: 1)
    - Roman history at the University of New Mexico, undated (Folder 18: 2)
    - Serb documents on July crisis (Serbiens Aussenpolitik 1908-1918), 1945 (Folder 18: 3)
    - Switzerland, 1997 (Folder 18: 4)
    - Thesis editing questions, 1941 (Folder 18: 5)
    - University of Michigan Convocation and Commencement, 1935-1942 (Folder 18: 6)
    - Western European holdings in the Indiana University library, undated (Folder 18: 7)
    - Will, 2001 (Folder 18: 8)
- Photographs, 1860-2001. (Box 8, 18)